Now, I don't know about you, but I'm in
the mood to keep talking about the
market revolution. But this time, let's
focus on how this development affected
US society and culture during this
period. It sounds real tasty to me. So,
if you're ready to get them brain cows
milked, let's get to it. Okay. So, I
reckon I should start by telling you
that one of the chief effects of the
market revolution was the growth of
cities, which is a phenomenon we call
urbanization. And for the most part,
city growth occurred in the north in
places like New York and Philadelphia.
But all cities that were growing were
geographically situated among major
trade routes, some of which were located
in the west. For example, Cincinnati,
Ohio became a major trade city owing to
its location on the Ohio River and
Rochester, New York grew rapidly on
account of its strategic position on the
Eerie Canal. So, the point you need to
remember is this. The cities that were
located along busy trade routes grew
rapidly during this period as new
infrastructure united the various
regions of the United States. And I
should mention that even though yes,
we're geeking out about the rapid pace
of urbanization during this period. The
United States was still primarily rural
and would be until about the 20th
century. But to add a further
complication, rural people were becoming
more connected to cities thanks to all
the transportation networks that sent
agricultural goods to cities and then
manufactured goods to rural areas. Oh,
and by the way, if you want to know guys
to follow along with this video and all
my videos, check that link in the
description. Okay, now trade routes and
strategic geography were not the only
reason cities were growing during this
period. No, another major contributor to
urbanization was immigration. Between
the 1820s and 1840s, more than 2 million
European immigrants arrived to the
United States, the bulk of which were
Irish, German, or Scandinavian. And why
says you did those millions of
immigrants relocate their hind parts to
America? Well says I, many of the Irish
who were at first mostly Protestant and
then later mostly Catholic came because
of widespread hunger on account of the
Irish potato famine which was worsened
by oppressive economic policies enacted
by the British. And then many Germans
also came because of lack of food due to
poor harvest and failed political
revolutions which left many of them
feeling marginalized. And the German
immigrants were mostly Lutheran but
there was also a strong minority of
Catholics and Jews as well. And look,
I'm not just flapping my mouth hole
about early 19th century immigration
statistics for funsies, although I'm
sure we can all agree this is real fun.
No, there are two big points to remember
here. First, a large portion of these
immigrants, especially the Irish,
settled in big cities in the north,
where they could find work in America's
growing industrial sector. And in doing
so, not only did these cities grow, but
they also became more ethnically and
religiously diverse. And side note, many
of the German immigrants migrated
further west to work on farms. And while
that did diversify the frontier, the
impact wasn't as significant as the
diversification of cities. Second, this
spike in immigration was intimately
connected to the market revolution since
those who settled in northern cities,
especially the Irish, provided an influx
of cheap labor for factories which then
powered the market revolution. Okay.
Now, the second major social consequence
of the market revolution was the
development of a more defined social
hierarchy. In other words, it became
increasingly clear who was on the top
and who was on the bottom. But before I
tell you about those new social
stratifications, let me tell you why
they emerged. Because it might not be
exactly obvious to you why a big
economic change would result in a
reordering of society. Okay, so remember
from the previous video that prior to
the market revolution, most people fed
and clothed themselves through
subsistence farming or at least
semi-subsistance farming. And that means
that most people grew what they needed
to eat and made what they needed to live
with their own hands.
>> You want a new shirt? Then thread that
needle, baby. You want a sandwich? Well,
I hope you're willing to wait about 6
months for the harvest to come in
because there ain't no Publix down the
road. But during an after the market
revolution, most goods, both industrial
and agricultural, were made for other
people to buy and sell on distant
markets. So that meant that a growing
number of Americans were working for
wages and therefore bought most of the
food and clothes that they needed to
survive. And the name for this wage
working group was the working class and
they occupied the bottom rung of the
social ladder. This was by far the
largest class and made up the bulk of
urban Americans who worked in factories
for pitifully low wages, which is why
they were sometimes referred to as wage
slaves. But don't worry, they also
endured pretty bleak working conditions,
too. So, you know, it was worth the low
wages. Anyway, many folks in the working
class were immigrants, but a significant
number of them were also young women.
And let me tell you a little bit about
both groups. So, working-class urban
immigrants, many of whom were Irish,
worked in low-wage industrial jobs that
Americans themselves were unwilling to
take. And while that had many positive
economic benefits that facilitated the
market revolution, the sheer number of
Irish immigrants simultaneously led to a
growing nivist backlash. Now, by
definition, nivism describes the
movement to protect the interests of the
nativeorn people against the influence
of foreign immigrants. And so with all
these Irish immigrants flooding the
cities with their Irish Catholic
cooties, American nivists were concerned
that such cooties were threatening
American Protestantism. And so nivists
beat nivists and they led efforts to
contain the Catholic contagion. For
example, on a couple of occasions,
nivists attacked Catholic convents
because, you know, if he can't even beat
up a meek Catholic nun, then are you
even a man? And maybe the most visible
nivist move was the creation of a
powerful anti-atholic political party
known as the Nothing Party. Okay. Also,
the working class was made up of a
significant number of young working
women. In fact, in the late 1820s,
several entire towns devoted to
manufacturing were constructed in New
England. The most famous of which was
located in Lowel, Massachusetts. And so,
the sponsors of this town recruited
young farm girls from the countryside to
work in their factories and live in
their towns. And for those girls who
agreed to go, their lives were managed
by a strict code. So, church attendance
was required, curfews had to be
observed, and their work was precisely
regulated by clocks in order to ensure
productivity. I mean, it's every young
girl's dream, right? Anyway, in the
beginning, many of these girls felt
satisfied in their work and thought
about the journey away from home as
something of an adventure. However, by
the 1830s, their working conditions
deteriorated as factory owners cut wages
and the factory town boarding houses
became entirely overcrowded. In
response, the Lowel girls and many other
women who worked in similarly
constructed industrial towns, began to
agitate for reform. And after several
strikes and protests, working women
joined together in the Lowel Female
Labor Reform Association, which was the
first women's labor union in the United
States. and their most vocal and
widespread effort was to advocate for a
10-hour workday instead of a 12-hour
workday. And their success was at best
mixed, especially since women had no
right to vote. But even so, the pressure
they exerted on the Massachusetts
legislature was immense. Okay, now let's
move on to the other groups. Now,
because the market revolution and
industrialization fundamentally changed
the nature of how people worked and how
people interacted with the economy, a
new social phenomenon emerged, namely
the rise of the middle class. And if
that doesn't sound familiar, then let me
h explain it up for you. So the market
revolution essentially divided American
society into three distinct tiers. On
the top was the business elite which
represented the smallest class but also
the wealthiest and most powerful. And in
general these were the owners of
factories or shipping companies or some
other like businesses that fit into the
essential structure of the market
revolution. And then you had the middle
class which was a brand spanking new
social designation that emerged as a
direct result of industrialization. Now
the middle class was composed of those
folks who were not as wealthy as the
business elite but wealthier than the
working class. And essentially middle
class work was intangible work. In other
words, middle- class folks didn't make
or produce anything that you could see
or touch. So, the middle class was
filled with lawyers and teachers and
doctors to name only a few, which is to
say, they did not get their hands dirty.
Today, it's what we'd call knowledge
work. You know, like work done with the
thinkythinky parts and not the grippy
grippy parts. And so, on the whole, the
middle class acted as managers of the
working class. And as this distinct
class began to emerge, they developed
their own set of values, including
robust education for their children,
religious affiliation, and sobriety. And
they also developed a unique concept of
gender roles and family structure. And
that's going to lead us right into the
next point. Okay. So finally, let's talk
about the significant shift in
conceptions of gender roles and family
structures that grew out of the market
revolution. And this was mainly a
phenomenon that occurred in the middle
class. Now one of the chief values of
the middle class, especially the upper
middle class, was that men should earn
enough money to support the entire
family. And that of course means that
middle-class women should not have to
work. And as a result of this shift, two
distinct social phenomena became
prevalent. First, middle-class men and
women were increasingly understood to
have separate spheres of existence and
responsibility. So, the male sphere was
defined by work outside the home and the
female sphere was defined by domestic
work inside the home. So, if you were in
the middle class, you abided by this
motto. Men work, women make the
sandwiches just as God intended. And to
middle-ass men, this arrangement was
basically the definition of liberty and
independence. And then to take it even
further, their homes were divided by
gender- coded spaces. For example, the
study belonged to the man and his male
companions, while the kitchen was the
domain of the women folk. Now, just to
be absolutely clear, this was a middle
class phenomenon. This kind of gender
separation was not present in the
working class since both men and women
had to work in order to make ends meet.
Anyway, the second and related social
phenomenon that emerged in the middle
class was the rise of the cult of
domesticity. You see, as the division
between women and men became
increasingly clear, the middle class
ladies grew a question mark over their
heads and started to wonder, huh, okay,
so how do I woman? And thankfully they
didn't have to wonder for very long
because as the social trend gathered
steam a flurry of publications emerged
including books and novels and magazines
which sought to define this new role in
which women found themselves. It became
known as the cult of domesticity and
under its influence middle-class women
learned that they were to fulfill their
social role by raising virtuous children
and providing their husbands with a home
kept to exacting standards.
Additionally, middle-class women
fulfilled their role as purchasers and
shoppers in the emerging consumer
economy. And in many ways, this was
merely an extension of the ideal of the
Republican motherhood that gained
traction after the revolutionary period.
And although this idea of female
submission and subordination would
become widespread in American society,
by the end of this period, we're going
to see a growing movement to challenge
it. But alas, I get ahead of myself. So,
we'll save that for another video. Okay.
You can click here to watch my other
videos from unit 4, or you can click
here to grab my video note guides, which
will help you get all the contents of
this course firmly crammed into your
brain fold. I'm glad you came around,
and I'll catch you on the flipflop. I'm
lur.